software engineering radio episode 2 dependencies.
[Music]
welcome to this episode of software engineering radio.
in this episode Marcos and Everhart talk about managing dependencies.
dependencies are a very important topic in software engineering.
and it's not easy in big projects to handle them correctly.
so before we go into detail on this topic I think we should discuss the prerequisites.
what do we expect the listener to know about object orientation?
so I think I'll just mention a couple of topics.
so I mean we don't want to provide an introduction to object orientation.
so we assume that that you the listener knows what classes are what objects are all these kinds of things.
you know that there are interfaces that you can let classes implement.
there is this concept of polymorphism.
so if you invoke an operation on an object then depending on the dynamic subtype of the declared class the respective method is invoked.
and also objects can have relationships.
so if you look at the UML diagram you can draw those Association lines between classes.
which means that at runtime objects instances of those classes have no each other and can talk to each other.
and and this podcast episode is actually about the relationships the associations between those objects.
between objects in general in terms of dependency.
so it's not really focused on inheritance for example.
and that's one of the one of the already quite interesting points.
because usually object orientation is really a lot of people think it's about inheritance.
because that gives us reusability and so on.
and if you do object oriented systems for some time you realize that in fact that's not the case.
it's not inheritance that is so important.
but it's rather delegation calling methods on other objects using other objects as so is provided for your own object.
and wiring things together.
so so that's probably one of the interesting points.
and it's in a way confusing that inheritance has become this first class good citizen that is available in all of the object-oriented languages.
while there is no real concept in terms of Delegates in right.
this is interesting to see because in the last episode we talked about patterns and the design patterns book the Goff book.
we talked about actually uses a lot of delegation.
so instead of using this it built-in feature of inheritance many of the patterns use delegation in a creative way.
to achieve flexibility that would not be possible by just using inheritance strategy for example right.
so also if you look at the UML language you can represent a relationship between classes as a first class construct right.
you have a line between classes so an association between objects is not implemented as an attribute that happens to have the type of the other end.
it's really a first class concept.
and in programming languages there there isn't this concept.
you can only add an attribute of the Apple type but you can't have associations explicitly.
and the most important part is that.
object orientation is really about deconstructing a system into smaller blocks.
and then borrowing all things together.
and this can only be done using dependencies and not using inheritance right.
also a final word on that inheritance is always static.
you have to statically define in your source code the class from which you inherit.
if you use delegation and associations between objects you can change a lot of these things at runtime.
so you're much more flexible.
even though I'm not sure whether this is the case for all object-oriented languages but that's probably a different topic.
yes so the question is why this is so important.
I think one of the main points why this is so important is because of testability.
because only if you have a flexible system and you can have a reduced set of objects wire together.
and test them in isolation you have a really easily testable system.
because other otherwise you can just get the whole thing and tested as a rule. and that's not a practical approach.
and I think especially concerning the quality of software and productivity and so on.
it's really testability that is the that is the the that is so important to keep in mind.
if you talk about if your dependencies and so on.
so if you generalize that a little bit it's basically about modularizing a system.
so you want to be able to extract some parts of the system and replace them with some other mock or stub.
so you can you can you can easily write or implement test scenarios.
if you are not able to manage your dependencies reasonably and if you pull on one Class B.
then then basically you pull and pull and pull and we have the whole system in your hand. you don't want that.
you want to be able to extract certain parts of the system isolate them.
provide an environment in which they feel at home so all their dependencies are satisfied.
and then you want to be able to test this part of the system in isolation from all the rest.
which is the same thing I mean then that's what I want to stress.
it's not about flexibility as a goal in itself.
it's rather something that is has the goal of testability that's the main reason.
it's not it's also not so much about reusability it's mainly because of testability.
and that's why it's probably too important.
ok and and another reason might not be the most important one.
but again you might want to be able to assuming your dependencies are dependencies on some infrastructure things.
like for example if you implement enterprise javabeans and inside your beam you have for inside your business logic.
you have dependencies on various j2ee artifacts such as Jay in the eye naming directory or something like that.
then you want to be able to control the dependencies to those technologies specific things.
in order to again be able to remove those technology specific things.
in order to have a more testable and more flexible system.
yeah but again the main reason my opinion is testability right.
it's not so much that you want to call the system later on to a different environment that is not Java EE right.
because that is rather seldom the case.
and it's also hard to really get the system to the point where this is easily doable.
so it's rather about having the flexibility to use use infrastructure probably not an application server to do tests.
now I think we kind of motivated what the problem is.
and also we explained that languages object-oriented languages don't easily help us there.
because there is no way to natively represent associations and dependencies.
so what are the classical means of solving that problem?
how our dependency is managed and in typical object-oriented systems?
I believe one of the ways to do it or one of the usual ways is more or less the factory pattern.
so it's about having one central part of the system class or whatever that is responsible.
for providing the individual objects that other object can depend on and satisfy those dependencies.
so so what does that mean?
so you have a little bit a piece of of application logic.
like for example assume we have component that calculates some insurance policies.
and then it needs to have some I don't know mathematical helper component.
so it would go in the implementation code you would go to the factory and say factory dot get mathematical helper component.
and then you would invoke operations on that one right.
yeah yeah that's basically the idea I guess. okay.
and I think there are other patterns that are closely related to that.
so for example there is a single which is basically it says that there should be one instance of the object available in the system.
but that's also a special case of the factory.
because it's it just says that you have one instance.
so every time you call the factory you get the very same instance.
so it's not I mean it's from from the point of view of so resolving dependencies is not really different.
and I think the same is also true for naming systems.
because it's also about one piece of the system that produces objects according to a certain given name.
so it's ultimately it's again a factory.
so I think it really boils down to that most of the approaches really victory base.
a naming system is basically a factory where one party of the system can register certain objects under a given name.
and another part of the system can then look up those objects using the name.
so the various parts of the system have to agree on a name.
and then the river the naming service or naming system or registry can be used to look them up.
so it's basically a factory whose contents are dynamically populated by another part of the system.
you know exactly, and I believe the point is it's from more from the distributed systems environment.
so I weigh the the disputer naming system DNS that you use in the Internet is also in a way a factory.
but I think the term naming system is rather from disputed systems.
and in in the field of distributed systems there are other concepts like trader for example.
where you specify certain product in in terms of attributes it has to have.
the visual hello world example it's a printer.
so you can say ok me here so you want this many pages and so on.
you get a printer somewhere in the net that provides this level of service.
so I think that's why there are two different names it's really because the background is different.
and in one case it's about distributed systems and in the other case it's of the factory it's about as usual object-oriented systems.
and those intermix for example in it should be COBOL Java environments.
so that's why there are two.
so what's the problem why why isn't the factory a good thing?
why not just use factories and and be happy?
the the metaphor that you could use it's despite and the web so the family tree is in the middle of this.
a dependency graph everybody knows the factory.
so if you start to drag one object one class from this dependency graph the next thing you get is factory.
and after that you could pass any pet everything.
so it means that you have to reuse parts of the systems or interchange parts of the system get quite hot.
because everybody really depends on the factory.
the the benefit of course is that.
you have the central part of the system where you could for example exchange implementation.
for a more communication can I can I give a different view?
I mean I agree that that factories are usually a problem.
and but I would argue from a different perspective.
so the problem is that if you have a factory that.
I don't know hosts ten different objects provides access to ten different objects.
now you you cannot tell whether a certain module which module uses which of those objects.
so the problem is if using a factory is something you have to do procedurally.
so in your implementation code somewhere deep down in your algorithms you can say factory get something.
you can even do this dynamically you can use reflection and all kinds of fancy things.
to come up with what you want to get from the factory.
as a consequence you cannot see UK if you look at the piece of code specifically at its signature.
you cannot see what dependencies it has.
compared this to to providing features if you have a class and this class provides certain operations.
then you can define an interface that declares those operations and your class implements that interface.
and now you can use for example an instance of tests and all object-oriented languages.
that very that can check whether this class provides the respective operations by just checking.
you know if class instance of this or that interface then you know that it provides those methods.
there is no such thing for the other way around.
you can't use any reflection or any other features to find out that this class requires a certain other class.
at runtime to do its work if you use the factory.
because the factory provides all kinds of things and what specifically a class needs is hidden in the implementation code.
so there is no way of using reflection or other rather simple tools to find out what dependencies a class has.
you have to kind of understand the application logic in order to find out what what what it talks queries from the factory.
and that's a problem.
and again jemelle is kind of advanced on this topic.
because in component diagrams you can easily say okay so this component offers those interfaces and uses these interfaces and that's it.
what what is quite hard to do in object-oriented languages or the usual object-oriented notion cities.
so so if we kind of try to come up with a criteria for an approach that doesn't have these these problems.
what kind of criteria would this approach or what the solution have to fulfill?
so for one it has to explicitly declare which resources it needs.
so if Class A wants to talk to object of Class B and C at runtime.
then it has to be clearly declared that a requires B and C.
so you need to have a way of marking this explicitly.
and then of course you have to have a way how your application code can access those objects.
so it's not enough to just declare what you need.
you also have to make sure that at runtime when the program runs you actually have a way to access what you need.
so if even if a module or a class declares the resource it resources it needs.
then yeah there must be somebody who provides those resources to the class at runtime.
so if you have a Class A and B and C again and a requires B and C.
then at runtime you need some magic that supplies instances of B and C to the instance of a.
another important thing if a class declares it requires P and C then it must not be able to access other resources.
because if we explicitly declare which resources we need in a class.
then we must make sure that there is no other way of accessing stuff that we did not explicitly declare.
so this is in my view the criteria a solution has to fulfill.
in order to be better than what we talked about before.
what it makes sense to elaborate on the topic with we are talking about classes now or components.
and what the differences because as our already pointed out at least in the human diagrams.
this is closely related two components.
and also this kind of explicit dependencies is part of the definition of component.
okay yeah so probably make sense to distinguish these kinds of things.
however one could say that a class that explicitly declares the resources it needs can be called a component.
okay the discussion concerning components is to me is quite quite interesting.
because usually the components are kind of associated with a heavy weight approach such as.
it should be in my opinion the distinction between class and components is not so clear-cut.
and I believe one thing that is quite important in this field.
and and it's a topic for at least some years now is dependency injection.
because this is one of the other new approaches and in really a basic approach of providing those dependencies.
and it's also rather ezv.
the idea is that you have an external entity that.
takes there are all those objects.
and provides them with the other objects it depends on.
so that's quite a simple idea basically it just says that you you get an instance of the object.
we tried to discover which other objects are needed by this object.
and then you try to satisfy those dependencies.
so and how do you do this how do you how does the object declare which resources it needs?
in a way it depends on the implementation so there are different ways of doing this.
for example one of the ways is to just declare some constructor parameters.
or you could have set up methods or attributes that can be set accordingly to certain other objects.
the last thing about this is that the explicit declaration of dependencies that. we were discussing.
is done in terms of the programming language.
and it's also quite is it also quite nicely fits into the general concept.
because usually so those concepts like instructors and parameters to constructors and param and some attributes that you can set.
I usually object-oriented concepts so it's nothing new that has to be added to actually get this.
but what you do need is you need some external let's call it container dependency general container.
that instantiates the objects that supplies resources to those objects using the setter operations or the constructor parameters right.
yeah and and how and how does the how do you configure the container.
so that the container knows which objects instantiated and and what I mean.
you know okay now so object class declares with resources it needs but how and then you instantiate this class using the container.
how do you tell the container which object not just which class which object it has to supply.
to those resource setters?
actually that also depends because in some environments like people container for example this is done automatically.
so you just say okay so these are my constructor parameters.
and if you happen to find anything that is type comfortable with those constructor parameters.
then there you go just set it and pass it to my constructor.
so it looks in all the objects it has and if there is an object of the type that the other one requires it passes that one in.
yeah anyway your us yeah I mean that's that's the art wiring approach.
other container other dependency injection moments like spring for example also provide other means.
where you explicitly declare which objects should be set to which attributes or properties and so on.
so there there is a great variety of possibilities.
so if we look at the flexibility you get from that there are actually I mean there are three levels of flexibility with regards to resources in general.
the first level is you don't even know the interface of the resource you're talking to.
the second level is you do know the interface but you don't know its implementation.
and the third level of flexibility you know it's interface you know the implementation.
but there might be several runtime objects instances of that implementation of that class.
and you can configure which of them you want to provide as a resource to a certain class.
and the approach of dependency injection it has discussed before allows us to use various to to wire which instance you want.
it also allows you to hide certain different implementations behind the same interface.
so it allows you this second and the third kind or way of flexibility right.
that's true, okay so you already mentioned Pico container.
what kind of I mean is there's a common technology those days is it used in in many environments?
or I mean I'm I'm a little bit biased.
so I in my opinion and also what I heard from other people is that if spring is actually the dependency injection container that.
is largely used.
and I think one of the nice things about spring is that.
you can use all these different techniques.
so you can have constructor dependency injector.
you can have dependency injection that is based on set methods you can have auto wiring I type.
you can have out wiring by giving certain names of the components and so on.
and therefore I believe it's quite a good approach.
and there are other things integrated into spring as well that makes it quite a valuable piece of code.
so that's what I think but as I said I'm biased.
biased because you're a big spring believer?
yeah and I'm working on a book all about it and so.
ok ok so if we evaluate this dependency injection strategy with regards to the criteria we came up with before.
so how does that how does that compare?
so I mean the setter operations like if a if either if there is class a that requires an instance of Class B at runtime.
then a would have an operation set B and then as the parameter P right.
so there would be a setter for an object of type B.
so this declares explicitly which resources you need you can use reflection to find out about them.
you have a means to access those resources because the container just calls the setter operation.
and in the inside the setter you typically store the object you just got past in an inner in a member variable.
and you can use that one later.
also of course you have this external entity which would be the dependency injection container.
that knows about all the instances and passes in the resources to the respective objects.
and finally you can't access any other resources from your implementation code.
because if you don't have a setter you have no way of getting access to those objects.
and if you have a setter you implicitly declare that you have an additional resource.
so this is this kind of fulfills our criteria.
yeah and the fun thing about it is that.
it's basically still the same thing.
so there is still this all-knowing factory out there that knows all the objects and so on.
but in terms of dependencies at the code level the factory totally disappears.
so that's kind of the the paradox.
so it's not buried the implementation logic it's it's explicit in the signature.
yeah exactly, and so how do you how do you how do you do testing with this approach?
how does this simplify testing in practice?
oh that's that's actually one of my more or less favorite topics.
because I believe that it's actually a big value proposition for using dependency injection containers.
so first of all you need to define what what you mean with the term testing.
the first thing that you get is you can do real unit tests meaning that you just test the class here itself in isolation.
because everything else can be said into it.
so that's one of the things the other thing that you get is you can easily change parts of the system.
and if for example you could say okay so I'm going to use a different database.
I'm not going to use an application server or I'm a certain subsystem will be replaced by reduce functionality for this test.
and you then you put all these things together in a test environment to test that.
that's not strictly it's not a unit test anymore.
because you don't have a class in the oscillation of this.
rather kind of an integration test of at least certain classes.
that's Ana sophoclean way whether unit tests are only allowed to test one single class.
I mean nobody does that in practice right?
it depends I mean the point is that.
certain functionalities it doesn't make sense the unit is. but the interesting part is that.
it's not just about having this class and I tested into isolation.
it's rather that you have this flexibility of also interchanging certain subsystems and so on. so it it really helps on a lot of different levels.
just it doesn't only have on the unit test level but rather during test cycle.
now all this dependency injection sounds really great.
however I think there are some critics say that there is the problem with magic.
so you just declare certain setters and then you start your dependency injection container.
and then by magic and there's some strange means of the definition and declaration and auto wiring and all these kinds of things.
you get a system that's somehow assemble together.
do you think that's a problem in practice?
did you experience that problem?
probably something that you don't feel comfortable with at least at the beginning.
but on the other hand I ultimately think that a lot about computer science and software development is about giving up control.
so for example I mean we clearly do have less control about what's actually happening in this.
and future object orientation and putting off a morphism and method call resolution that is done at runtime and virtual machine and so on.
so I can relate to that.
but on the other hand I think it's not really such a big problem in practice.
the other thing that you have to take into account is or that you have to think about this is how do you model arise your comparation.
and the other thing is there is no that's again going back to their components and classes.
it's fine it's quite fine-grained what we are talking about it's yes class level.
so I believe in a way you have to think about more coarse-grained approaches.
so it needs to come up with modules in your system that I wire together that you can replace.
that have have their own configuration files and so on. and that's something that you have to come up with yourself.
it's not something that the dependency injection system gives you.
that's actually a good point this this brings me to the to the question.
of I mean we were basically talking about the class level this is a very as you said a fine-grained level.
if we look at more higher levels like for example the dependencies between layers.
like you were only allowed to access model franck functionality from the GUI layer not the other way around.
then this dependency management thing goes up one level and it's not about classes anymore necessarily.
it might be about package dependencies or on another levels of granularity.
and we didn't talk about that that's maybe a different episode.
to illustrate that dependency injection is not necessarily the the only approach that satisfies satisfies the criteria we presented before.
I just wanted to briefly give another thing.
so the problem with the factory and the naming systems is that.
they are typically global.
that means that all objects are in there that means everybody in their implementation code can access all the objects that are in the factory.
so if we had a specific factory for each class which contained only those objects that are kind of legal for that class to access.
then we wouldn't have the problem right.
so if we find a way of coming up with specifically configured classes fudge sorry specifically configured factories for each class.
then that would be that would solve the same problem.
and and one way to do this is if you work in the in the context of model driven systems.
if you use a model driven software approach and what you can do is you can specify your dependencies in the model.
like for example in a UML diagram using UML the dependencies or associations.
and then if you generate a class X from that you can also generate an object called X factory.
and this X Factory contains accessor methods for only those resources.
for which you declared dependencies in the model by using UML dependencies or associations.
so then you use you still access the factory from the implementation code.
the access to your factory object like Factory get such-and-such is kind of still buried in the implementation code.
but the big advantage is you can only access those things for which we have declared dependencies explicitly in the model.
because if you didn't declare them the generated factory wouldn't include those objects.
and therefore you can't access them.
so so the problem is not necessarily the fact that you access the factory from implementation code.
it's that it contains all objects of the system and you never know which objects you look up from the implementation code.
using this specifically generated Factory this problem can also be solved so this is another approach.
yeah but I mean either the question to me would be using a model driven approach.
you could also use a dependency injection infrastructure as yes the basis.
so the question to me would be whether if you compare those two approaches.
having a specific victory for each whatever class and using dependency injection what the benefit is.
if you just use this factory approach I mean it's nothing nothing I just wanted to illustrate.
that the problem is not inherently with the factory but with the fact that it's usually a global thing.
where everything is registered and everybody can access everything.
and you you satisfy those requirements we outlined before either through dependency injection or through other means.
if you have ways of tweaking it so that it actually works.
and I mean writing factories for each class manually is not something you'd like to do.
but if you generate stuff anyway then this is an approach.
what do you do if you can't use the pen Injection or some of the other magic we just talked about?
other other means of kind of trying to get your dependencies under control.
actually accounting of any cases where you can't use dependency injection.
so I mean if you have an existing system that uses a factory based approach and it's quite large.
then introducing a dependency injection is probably not the way to go.
because it's just so much effort that you have to spend.
but I think it's it's how to come up with cases where you can't really use dependency injection.
but that's probably a different thing.
I mean that there are other things to kind of come to grips with your dependencies.
for example you can use tools like dependency software tomograph for example which allows you to visualize dependencies.
there is another tool on SourceForge which is called depth find for dependency finder.
which which can allows you to do the same thing.
so this doesn't it kind of doesn't control your dependencies but it helps you see them.
other things is for example you can use aspectj to kind of lock the dependencies you have.
or even you could write static compile time aspects that that output an error message.
if you access code or resources which you kind of shouldn't.
like if you have a UI layer and a model layer and the model layer accesses the UI layer which is not allowed.
then you can write a compile time aspect that says whenever a class in that package accesses code from another package.
then output an error message.
yeah and if there are other tools I mean we could also mention solar tray or the metrics plugin for eclipse right.
they basically do the same thing.
and actually that's probably one of the drawbacks of dependency injection.
if you have really rely on things like auto airing and so on there is a certain lack of tools.
so for example in the spring world I don't know of any tools.
I mean I'm not sure whether I'm pretty sure that there isn't any tool that provides you with graph of the dependencies in the system.
if you rely on auto wiring.
so dependency injection is not a magic bullet it's not a silver bullet. but it it helps quite a bit.
it's interesting to see that mainstream infrastructures such as for example enterprise javabeans also adopt this approach now.
an EJB three dependency injection is the way to to connect components right.
as I said I'm biased so a colleague of mine did in a variation of the adventure builder.
because there was no ported to Java EE.
what's the adventure builder?
that's one of those example applications that use to be pedestal.
and no it's called manager builder.
so it was done on a j2ee one finds its now ported to Java EE 5.
and D the fun thing about it is probably the sad thing about it is that you end up with code that.
still relies on jndi.
instead of a naming system instead of using dependency injection.
but but I thought but I thought HIV 3 uses dependency injection?
yeah that's that's exactly the problem the problem is it should be use dependency injection.
so as soon as you know ok a different class in normal class like like or or servlets or all these kinds of things also those Java each class.
I mean if as far as I know everything as I said it's something that one of my colleagues did.
as far as I know also the other Java artifacts like software's and so on can be dependency injected.
but if you do simply you to class that has to have access to the data source to write a non managed class.
yeah then you end up using using chain di to look it up or it can pass it in as a parameter.
yeah but I mean either way it's not probably what you want to do.
and the other thing is that.
in in Java 5 you'd declare those dependencies using annotations right.
and in my opinion the approach of using just normal interface normal class them normal methods or constructor parameters is better.
but I mean but it's just my opinion.
although of course using using annotations you can specify more criteria right.
for example instead of just saying you know there is a setter that expects an object of type such-and-such.
you can use an annotation that says I need not just any object but an object with these and those properties. so that that does have its benefits.
but the drawback in my opinion is that.
you statically at compile time and Ryan I draw structure.
and that's probably I mean it's so you end up having your business could depend on annotations from eg B.
and I mean they write what you want right.
and also if you use annotations to specify the specific criteria that should be look used for for finding the resource. and that's probably not a good thing.
because typically you don't want to specify those criterias when you code.
but rather later when you deploy.
and when you deploy you have no way of changing you know the stuff you you you you wrote down as annotations.
yeah so okay so there are ways to do that in trouble.
yes I know so you can override the annotations through external specifications draining the ions phone.
so I mean the point to me is I don't see each other being superior to approaches like spring for example.
oh you're biased right?
yeah yeah that's true but I mean we'll see about that.
I'm I'm looking forward about to see to get more experiences with real-world systems and success stories virtually if I purchase and so on right.
it's going to be interesting.
okay so I think before we finally wrap up this episode.
I think it's worth mentioning that of course if you found out that you have too many complicated criss-crossing dependencies.
then it's a good thing of redistributing responsibilities between classes or other building blocks.
so that the number of dependencies actually is reduced.
however and that's the point about which we discussed today you first have to find out what those dependencies are.
and if they're hidden in implementation code it's a very hard thing to do.
and that's where dependency injection and the other things we talked about can really help.
to kind of make dependencies obvious.
yeah okay anything else you want to say?
yeah I just want to stress again the point of it's pregnant.
that you need more coarse-grained layer that's probably the other thing that you have to take into it to think about.
because most of the time we were talking about dependencies among objects.
and there is this other layer that is quite important as well.
and dependency injections we didn't know no solution for that I think.
or at least you have to think about how to make it a solution for these things.
that's probably also where whatever movement Roach's fit into the picture.
so it seems like this is a good point where we could hint on some potential future episode.
where we could discuss those architectural dependency management issues, yeah okay so that's it for today okay.
this was another episode of software engineering radio.
for general information feedback and past episodes go to se - radio net.
soft engineering radio wants to thank Henning parley for providing the music views on the show.